<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Waldemar Panas&#39; blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Waldemar Panas&#39; blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Waldemar Panas</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>BlockHound can save you from waking up at midnight</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/blockhound-can-save-you-from-waking-up-at-midnight/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/blockhound-can-save-you-from-waking-up-at-midnight/</guid>
      <description>BlockHound detects problems that will take down your reactive applications It might not be that self-evident, but your non-blocking reactive application can block and eventually run out of computing power. It&amp;rsquo;s simple to make that error. All you have to do is use a blocking operation, and everything falls apart like a house of cards. It can disguise itself as an undocumented method with an unintended side-effect or a misused dependency.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to migrate MongoDB</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/how-to-migrate-mongodb/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/how-to-migrate-mongodb/</guid>
      <description>MongoDB is advertised as &amp;ldquo;schemaless&amp;rdquo; and it&amp;rsquo;s true. Until you need to make a breaking change to documents stored in your collection.
In that situation you realize that using schemaless database doesn&amp;rsquo;t free from migrating data when it&amp;rsquo;s structure changes.
How to do it in most efficient fashion? Let&amp;rsquo;s say you have tens of millions of documents in your collection. At that point this question changes to: how to do it without technical break?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leader Only Spring Boot Starter</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/leader-only-spring-boot-starter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/leader-only-spring-boot-starter/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Two weeks ago I released a library leader-only-spring-boot-starter. It leverages Apache Curator to restrict computation to a single application node. Underneath the library use LeaderLatch. All this is backed by Apache Zookeeper. If you want to use it, you need to have Zookeeper up &amp;amp; running. The library was created for applications that are developed with Spring Boot.
Usage First of all you need to add dependency to your project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Best way to handle unknown enum values using Jackson</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/best-way-to-handle-unkown-enum-values-using-jackson/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/best-way-to-handle-unkown-enum-values-using-jackson/</guid>
      <description>In this article I want to show you how to handle enums using Jackson. It not as easy as it seems. Jackson can&amp;rsquo;t handle unknown enum values by default. You have to decide, what to do. If you don&amp;rsquo;t, your application will fail, when external resource changes and new enum value is added.
How to handle unknown values? Since Jackson 2.0, you can use READ_UNKNOWN_ENUM_VALUES_AS_NULLfeature. Still you will have to handle null, when unknown value appears in deserialized enum.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Best Machine Learning tutorials</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/best-ml-tutorials/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/best-ml-tutorials/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The best way to learn something is to start doing it. This thought guides me through my career and it never failed me. In this short article, I will give you a quickstart to master machine learning.
Before you start doing tutorials about machine learning, you should learn Python. There are many resources to do that. For newbies I recommend learnpython.org. For those, who are familiar with programming, go straight to Learn Python 3 in Y minutes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to setup reactive client with OAuth in Spring Boot</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/this-week-i-learned-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/this-week-i-learned-5/</guid>
      <description>WebClient with OAuth I started a new project with WebFlux and wanted to access API with OAuth2 authorization. The official documentation for setting up OAuth2 with WebFlux was helpful, but not quite covered my case. Later, I found Baeldung&amp;rsquo;s article &amp;ndash; Spring Security OAuth Login with WebFlux. I tried using his solution, but UnAuthenticatedServerOAuth2AuthorizedClientRepositoryexception was thrown, when I booted the application up. I searched and found the final peace at StackOverflow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to share knowledge at Code Retreat</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/this-week-i-learned-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/this-week-i-learned-3/</guid>
      <description>Code Retreat 2019 Krystian Adamski, my teammate, sparked the idea and eventually organized on Friday a Code Retreat event in Allegro. He and Karol Teske did an excellent job in Poznań. I&amp;rsquo;m sure that my colleagues from Warsaw have similar opinion of Maciej Szarliński, Bartosz Balukiewicz and Kamil Halicki, who organized the event there.
It was a blast! I appreciate the atmosphere and shared knowledge. The most developing thing were the retrospectives after each of the sessions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Architecture Guilds, Event-driven systems and talk at University</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/this-week-i-learned-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/this-week-i-learned-4/</guid>
      <description>Architecture Guilds Jakub Nabrdalik had a talk about mistakes made when moving to microservices at GeeCon Prague 2019.
  You can watch it also in polish from Confitura 2019.
  He did a thesis that majority of companies that migrated to microservices from a legacy monolith made similar mistakes. From his experience as a consultant, he described what was done poorly and how to do it better.
Big part of talk was about software architecture and how it was enforced in companies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clean architecture with Victor Rentea, working with legacy code and sentiment analysis</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/this-week-i-learned-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/this-week-i-learned-2/</guid>
      <description>Victor Rentea at Devoxx Belgium If you read article from the previous week, you might think that I&amp;rsquo;m Victor Rentea&amp;rsquo;s fanboy. And you goddamn right! This time Victor had a talk about clean code and refactoring. The best part of his talk was the live-coding session. Victor made an architecture kata and it felt like a big mob programming. Must watch! However, I must warn you. It is over 2 hours.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Property-based testing, usefulness of HATEOAS and Victor Rentea awesomeness</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/this-week-i-learned-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/this-week-i-learned-1/</guid>
      <description>Every week I try to learn something new and grow as a software developer. I want to journal my discoveries and share them with community.
Property-based testing This week I attended my local JUG. SoftwareMill was celebrating it&amp;rsquo;s 10 year anniversary. They organized two talks for us. First one was about property-based testing. You can read the slides, but I warn you that they are in polish.
I&amp;rsquo;ve never given a much thought about property-based testing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why you should read Accelerate</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/why-you-should-read-accelerate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/why-you-should-read-accelerate/</guid>
      <description>Nicole Forsgren, Jez Humble and Gene Kim published Accelerate: The Science of Lean Software and DevOps: Building and Scaling High Performing Technology Organizations in March 2018.
First time I got to know about Accelerate was when I read Technology Radar. This book took first place in the section Techniques. Specialists, that wrote that report, said that you need to adopt knowledge from this book.
As Technology Radar indicates, many years of research preceded the publication of Accelerate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting started with RSocket</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/getting-started-with-rsocket/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/getting-started-with-rsocket/</guid>
      <description>In this article I will present you how to use RSocket with Spring Boot.
What is RSocket? RSocket is a bi-directional message-driven communication protocol. It features an advanced communication flow beyond standard request/response. You can response with a single message, a stream of messages or don&amp;rsquo;t response at all. A server can also start a communication on an established channel with a client.
RSocket allows you to communicate using following transport protocols:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Dagger 2 in Android with Kotlin</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/using-dagger-2-in-android-with-kotlin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/using-dagger-2-in-android-with-kotlin/</guid>
      <description>What made me do this article? I started programming Android applications few months ago. I went through fundamental and more advanced guides. None of them mentioned dependency injection. Without it I struggled to make proper unit tests. I decided that I have to make it work.
I looked around and found Dagger 2. The project developed by Google that provides dependency injection for Android applications. Sadly, I had a hard time making it work with Kotlin.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring I/O 2019</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/spring-io-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/spring-io-2019/</guid>
      <description>The future of Spring Framework is reactive and it is at your fingertips.
The opening keynote The Spring I/O conference took place in Barcelona at 16-17 May 2019. Big names of Spring Framework like Ben Hale and Jürgen Höller presented what is up with Spring in 2019.
  The most frequent topics The recurring topic of last years is reactive programming. Ben Hale and Jürgen Höller proved that they are aware of poor data access and networking tooling.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Android - learning resources</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/android-learning-resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/android-learning-resources/</guid>
      <description>Where to start? I write this article from perspective of Java programmer. So I assume that you already know Java and Gradle.
Before you start making mobile apps, it&amp;rsquo;s good to know Kotlin. I recommend you to try out Kotlin Koans. It&amp;rsquo;s an easy to follow series of exercises that will help you have a grasp of programming in Kotlin.
A good beginning with a mobile application development is the Build your first app guide.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring Batch - JPA to XLSX with Apache POI</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/spring-batch-jpa-to-xlsx/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/spring-batch-jpa-to-xlsx/</guid>
      <description>What is Apache POI? Apache POI is a Java library that allows reading and writing Microsoft Documents. It supports Excel, Word, PowerPoint and even Visio.
In this article I will focus on Excel and its current file format XLSX. Apache POI provides low-memory footprint API, SXSSF, for writing to XLSX files. You can specify how many rows are processed in the memory by setting a sliding window. If number of rows exceeds the size of the window, they are flushed to temporary files.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Build your own projects repository using Maven</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/maven-build-your-own-projects-repository/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/maven-build-your-own-projects-repository/</guid>
      <description>What is Maven? Apache Maven is a development tool that simplify building and managing dependencies of projects. It uses a XML file called pom.xml for configuration.
What is a Maven repository? A repository in Maven is a list of ready to use artifacts. If you add a repository to your pom.xml file, you can use any of its artifacts as a dependency for your project. You can also use projects that are locally stored on your computer without repository.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elasticsearch - Fix an incompatible type</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/elasticsearch-fix-an-incompatible-type/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/elasticsearch-fix-an-incompatible-type/</guid>
      <description>What is Elasticsearch? Elasticsearch is a search and analitycs engine. It allows you to store data and search through it with ease, but it is not a database engine per se. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t guaranties ACID. Elasticsearch stores data in the index. It is special construction that fastens search queries, but it is vulnerable for corruption. It&amp;rsquo;s not a problem since all your data should be stored in proper database engine like MySQL or MongoDB, so index can be rebuilt from it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SDKMAN! - Multiple versions of Java</title>
      <link>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/sdkman-multiple-versions-of-java/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.wpanas.eu/posts/sdkman-multiple-versions-of-java/</guid>
      <description>What is SDKMAN! SDKMAN! is a development tool that allows you to install and manage Java, Scala, Groovy, Maven and many other tools, libraries and programming languages united under JVM platform. It is created for GNU/Linux&amp;rsquo;s and MacOS&#39; users.
Installation The first step is to paste this command in your terminal and submit it.
curl -s &amp;#34;https://get.sdkman.io&amp;#34; | bash This will launch the process of installation, which might require your input.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
